[Music]
thank you
foreign
[Music]
hello everyone welcome this is active
live stream number 51.1 we are in the
second discussion of our this paper
canonical neural networks perform active
inference
welcome to the active inference
Institute we're a participatory online
Institute that is communicating learning
and practicing applied active inference
you can find us on this slide and this
is recorded in an archived live stream
so please provide us feedback so we can
improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and will follow good video
etiquette for live streams
head over to activeinference.org to
learn more about the Institute and how
to participate in projects and learning
groups
all right
we're in active stream number 51.1 and
having our first
non-solo discussion on this paper
canonical neural networks perform active
inference
and really appreciative
particular that you've joined today it's
going to be a great discussion we'll
begin with introductions I'll say hello
and then please just jump in however
you'd like and we can start by setting
some context so I'm Daniel I'm a
researcher in California and I was
interested in this paper because we've
been talking a lot about active
inference from a variety of different
perspectives from the more fundamental
math and physics to some applications
philosophy embodiment all these really
interesting threads and this paper seems
to make a really clear meaningful
contribution and connection by
connecting active inference entities and
this approach of modeling to neural
networks which are in daily use globally
so thought it was a fascinating
connection and
really appreciate that we can talk about
this today so to you and welcome
go for it to kuya however you'd like to
introduce and say hello oh yeah uh hi
I'm a neuroscientist in English
Institute in Japan uh I'm particularly
interested in no Universal
characterization of neural network on
the brain using mathematical techniques
so uh this work I believe uh important
as a link between you know uh active
influence aspect vegan influencer aspect
of the brain and the dynamic card system
aspect of the neural network so uh I'm
very happy to join these discussions
thank you for invitation nice to meet
you
nice to meet you as well
um
the first thing you added the universal
characterization of neural networks
what is the universal characterization
of neural networks why is it being
pursued in this area of research
so as a narrow sense uh my
aim main aim of this paper is that so
you know
people people use active influence
formalization to characterize uh uh
brain activity Behavior so on and so on
but which
would be different from a conventional
neural network so there is a across of
problem uh
which is associated with the
conventional neural network and it is
not very clear whether uh all
characterization of conventional neural
network can be explained by active
reinforcement as a principle or not so
here Universal characterization means
that characterization of every aspect of
conventional neural network
which is a kind of dynamical system
derived uh as the association between a
physiological phenomena and so simple
mathematical formula using typical using
differential equations
but the broad sense I think a universal
characterization
means that
well
uh it is the characterization of brain
intelligence but it's a big picture and
what uh the paper particularly address
is only uh one aspect of the the four
picture
all right
so it'll be great to pull back to really
understand what synthesis is happening
so I'm going to ask what makes a neural
network model a neural network model and
what makes an active inference model in
active inference model is this synthesis
and connection you've made
true because of what
because of
you know basically what we showed
it's the the mathematical equivalence
between the formulation of canonical
neural networks and the formulation of
active inference in the sense that we
showed that uh a class of neural network
can be characterized by the minimization
of some particularly possible cost
function and we show that that cost
function can be lead as a
under particular class of GMT model
uh in terms of very non-partially
observable polymorphous position process
all right
shall we perhaps walk through some of
the sections of the paper
it would be awesome just
for each of these sections
maybe the numbered in the lettered
sections what does the section aim to
show and why was it there in the paper
oh
so uh
yeah briefly so
it's a it'll overview right uh so yeah
briefly so first we uh
introduce
uh so the main Management program our
interest which is a relationship to
which
is that so we we try to make a formal
ring between neural network and activity
influence that's uh that's the main
problem uh background and then we first
formalize formulate uh the equivalence
mathematical equivalence in a very broad
manner so in the first section in result
we formulate the
the the relationship using uh uh
concrete grass theorem which is a very
known statistical stereo
proposed very long time ago
and we using that we
link a general form of neural network
with a Jr form of variational data
impress but uh a program is that this
characterization does not addresses a
specific hormone generative model
which is crucial to characterize you
know
a specific specific model specific
neural network Dynamics so uh in the
following uh sections we characterize
the problem using common DB or partially
autism remark condition process and the
link that model with a particular class
or canonical neural network
and then we simulated
we use the simulation to to
corroborate that property in terms of
some maze tasks
all right thank you for this
could we talk about the complete class
theorem
so what is the scope of the complete
class theorem
and why was it the relevant set of the
neural networks to pursue or the right
way to frame it
yeah thank you for asking that so I like
uh the the slide you showed in the last
week's video so uh completely crosstalk
basically indicate that relationship
between uh some crossover decision and
Beijing inference
here a crucial keyword is a domicibility
or a domicible decision rule which is a
rule which is uh as the same as
uh as as good as the other
uh decision rules or at least in a
at the one point uh better than other
this genre so yeah simply speaking to
automation with the indicator in some
sense it is the best uh rule for some
aspect and usually we characterize such
a goodness using uh cost function loss
function or risk function and here what
we did is some we
established some association with this
this type of gross function risk
function with uh uh function of
canonical neural network which is we
call Cost function or biological
approachable cost function for neural
networks so our assumption is that a
neural network minimize cost function so
if it achieved the minimization and it
is a
obviously achieved some sort of
optimality so we can say it is a
domicible with respect to that cost
function so
the beauty of uh complete cross theorem
is that if we we find some admissible
decisions then automatically we can say
that it is this based on inference in
terms of in terms of some Vision cost
function with a generative model or
prior beliefs
so this the computer crease theorem is
crucial as a you know abstract
characterization of the relationship
between combustion and neural network
architecture Dynamics and variational
major influence
right
thank you
um
what does it mean when you said it was
biologically plausible of a loss
function
the time is a little bit arbitrary
because so in this paper we mean by uh
that is very possibility
by you know
the in the sense that
this neural network model can be derived
from realistic neural model through some
approximation
and so
here biological probability
suggests or means
you know
probability as a neural model synaptic
processity model
and if this cost function loss function
can derive such a closable algorithm
then we can say that this cost functions
are reportable
so what is the distinction between those
neural and synaptic components in the
loss function or what equation to look
at
uh you mean distinction between
neurodynamics and synaptic yeah what is
the distinction between them and how is
it represented in the equations
uh okay uh basically new activity
equation means a differential equation
about a variable that represents the
firing intensity or some sort of
variables associated with the neural
neural firing
on the other hand a synaptic elasticity
equation means
uh update rule about the synaptic weight
or synaptic strings is
which is a connection between two
neurons
and
a beauty of this formulation
proposed in this paper is that we
characterize both neural activity
equations synoptic processity equations
in terms of uh
well
Guardian this on a same cost function
using common cause function
so uh we can we can say that
if we consider the
partial derivative of some cost function
with respect to neural activity then it
derives the gradient descent rule about
activity
where if we consider a partial
derivative of cross-function f with
respect to synoptic weight then we
derive a synoptic processity rule
are those the only two aspects of a
neural network or why are those the two
key aspects
uh
it is a main kind of I I think it's a
it's a main
body of the new activity if we we
consider some uh
in for us running our action
exhibit by neural network in the sense
that a new activity correspond to fast
Dynamics fast gradient Dynamic links and
wire synaptic plasticity indicators
through dynamics that minimize risk
function cost function but in general we
can consider any any aspect any
variables associated with neural network
for example at least what we shown in
the paper is any free parameter which
may be associated with a hiring
threshold
or although we don't discuss in this
paper it will be possible to add other
variables related to neural network for
example we here we ignored uh
contribution of Grier Factor
but it will be possible to add the gr
factor in this formulation or any other
aspect of virus called neural network
um
that's very interesting and it speaks
also to a generate a general separation
of time scales for example in different
multi-scale systems or in the
renormalization group where it's
describing some
minimal multi-time scale system
where the faster time scale can be seen
as perception like at a slower time
scale can be seen as more learning like
and then in some hierarchical model
what's learning of one time scale can be
perceptual for a slower time scale so
it's a very
nice generalization
are there any examples of
decision rules that will help us think
about the action components of what the
neural network is doing because it may
be more familiar to think about digit
characterization and image
classification some kind of classical
tasks for neural networks
but how does the decision rule play out
in the context of neural networks
uh
okay
so in this paper we basically assume a
closed loop
so comprising a neural network part and
environmental part
so neural receives sensory input from
environment and feed
provide some feedback to the environment
so uh in
yeah even with the example of Digit
classification we can say that output
correspond to classifier classification
output which is the kind of is General
more relevant example would be for
example controlling agent like a robot
control or any kind of controlling or
decision making tasks for example where
we
encounter some Choice tasks we need to
advertise a for example left over right
or something any kind of such a
decisions can be associated with the
Adobe Mississippi or Atomic civil
decision
rule
so what would an example of an
irremissible
or admissible strategy be in the
decision-making task
uh
a domicibility
usually characterized by
loss function or risk function so if
so here in a domicivity indicate that
this there is another decision rule
which is uh at least one
Point better than the the the the
forecast
decision rule so
yeah simply speaking in other visibility
indicate that it that that this rule is
not better not not good
that negatively
but let's just say our decision rule is
we always turn right
is that an example of a decision rule
because there might be settings where
that is strictly effective and the
simplest rule whereas there's other
settings where that's going to be tragic
so what does it mean to be admissible
for an agent in light of different
Environmental contexts
that's a that's an interesting point so
even with even such a so two months
simpler and simplified rule it it can be
admissible under some particular
situation particular loss function
for example
that always turn right maybe maybe the
best under some some situation right so
uh the the the the the relationship of
administibility or enough security
depends on both Asian Asian
characteristic and the environmental
characteristic
foreign
s of the environment
uh for example for example if that
decision rule matches the the structure
architecture or environment then
you know maybe that that decision always
stand right uh achieved the shortest
past right
under some situation some environment
how does this admissibility help us
think about like overfitting
and how does it help us think about the
way that different practices are used
for neural networks to prevent them from
being over fit in practice
well
well uh the strictly Ado Mississippi is
characterized with the the bayesians so
we
uh and they uh we we cannot over love a
hidden state of the the environment uh
only we can observe uh is a part of the
entire
universe so uh the question is an
important question is uh what is the
best choice and such a limited limited
information Limited uh
uh yeah information so uh this uh
Bayesian this idea of admissibility or
complete Crest theorem uh
tell us that so you know
well-known Beijing
only the well-known Beijing Beijing
framework it achieved the admissive
admissibility adammissible decision
which means that uh
in this aspect Bayesian optimization is
give us a best best choice towards the
otherwise
we all Buffy or
or find would find the you know
sub-optimal solution
so it's a nice nice Association nice
linkage between the decision what is a
good decision about the decision and the
more established statistical inference
basically inference framework
thank you that's very
helpful so
we're reducing our
uncertainty and risk
about hidden states in the environment
so in the special case where the entire
environment is observable without error
like a chess game
then
there's an equivalence between
calculation of risk or loss on
observables or on hidden States but
they're not really hidden
but they are environmental States
whereas any amount of uncertainty
in the mapping between
observations and hidden states which is
usually shown as a in the partially
observable Markov decision process
any amount of uncertainty about
unobserved or partially observed
environmental States
enables you to fit your uncertainty
optimally about that hidden state
and fit that uncertainty simply
with a gradient descent and by doing so
you don't overfit a model of observables
which might be the fallacy or the issue
with simply doing descriptive statistics
you might get an infinitely small
variance
with a frequencest estimate because you
have a hundred thousand data points so
the variance
from a descriptive statistics
perspective might be very small
[Music]
I think it speaks very much to
why neural networks are useful in
practice from training with limited data
sets
because that's an empirical observation
that they don't entirely overfit but
also I'm sure there's ways to construct
them
that are overfit
yeah
foreign
[Music]
optimal priorities for example
well
I'm not sure
it's
either
over it in the sense what you mentioned
because if we select some priority then
the Bayesian function itself changes and
the neural networks that try to fit to
that cost function so those function
minimization will be achieved about even
such a situation but that solution is
not good for our you know original
purpose
that's a tall keypad yeah that
um is reminiscent of some discussions
we've had discussing like
driving off a cliff or blowing up is
also reducing free energy like dropping
off a building reduces your potential
energy and so there are potentially
decision making or strategic
trajectories
that do for some time Horizon
minimize free energy
yeah perhaps even or maybe even
guaranteed better than some longer time
Horizon because if the short-term
strategies Were Somehow better than the
long-term Horizon
it would be difficult to imagine because
the long-term Horizon would be at least
as good as a short-term strategy
so that speaks to the challenges of
planning
in action so how is planning addressed
in
modern neural networks
and how does this work help us think
about that
uh that's another very important aspect
so uh first
I have to say that uh this framework
addresses a planning aspect but that
that planning is not necessary
the the optimal or
the optimal solution in the sense that
what we interested in is uh optimization
or planning under a limited structure
the
structure is characterized by here but
Korea neural networks
so yeah planning
occurred by an association between
risky in the future and the decision our
decision in the past here we model that
aspect using a
delayed modulation of cyanotic
plasticity mediated by some neural
modulator or neurotransmitters
this is the model
as a
product of the the risk property and
heavier product uh on the the
cost function neural network function
all right I'm gonna ask a great question
from the chat and then we'll look at the
figures a little closer so ml Dawn wrote
a question stuck in my mind for a long
time could you please put it to rest do
we need to have knowledge about all
states possible actions and sensory
inputs for active inference
well uh
you mean if you seek the exact solution
exact optimal solution then
maybe more information
would help you to find out
but under some uh Model A gently model
under some uh idea ideal assumption then
uh the old or viology not necessary to
achieve
the
optimize optimal pollution
I know that I'm not sure if I correctly
answer your point
so just to restate it facilities of
course knowing all the states possible
actions and sensory inputs it's not a
bad thing worst case there's some
computational complexity trade-offs but
the problem becomes fully stable
but
I think ml Dawn is asking about cases
where you don't know
all of the
State spaces or potentially even the
dimensionality or the semantics of
hidden States active States sensory
inputs and why not even add cognitive
States
so in not just partially observed but
partially known State spaces
how are these addressed
in neural networks and how does active
inference help us think about it
uh okay I think the questions about the
how can we separate those
States like a sensory function internal
external
how can we separate
not just in principle have these states
be separated
but deal with the fact that some of
these states we might have
good knowledge on
and some states like the hidden States
we might not even know like we don't
know the dimensionality of the cause
vector in the world I see
for example in terms of dimensionality
there is a statistical technique to
estimate the dimensionality for example
various
information criteria like information
criteria based and information correctly
all of them try to inform or estimate a
plausible dimensionality about the
experimental environmental hidden States
so so there is analogy with those
information criteria and the vibrational
query energy minimization to with
version of minimization we can we can
identify a plausible plausible model
structure which in principle involved
the dimensionality aspect
but in terms of neural network
in this paper we don't
carefully consider about the
dimensionality optimization because
we've
we first defined the number of neuron
and don't change during training
but in principle we can consider
the change in the number of neurons
which is associated with the the
increasable neurogenesis adult
neurogenesis or development during the
event development stage
that would be a important extension
[Music]
of these this this this direction
that's very interesting
here's
um a remark
well one no is
equation one
summarizes a lot of what you've been
describing
there's a parallelism or a concordance
being drawn between the loss function of
neural networks and the variational free
energy of the parameterized model
there so
to come back to these processes
that influence learning which we could
think of as the neural network becoming
more fit from A Loss function
perspective or the variational Bayesian
partially observable Markov decision
process
entity generative model becoming better
at doing what it does so there's the
firing rate on the neural network side
the synaptic plasticity at a slower time
scale which we discussed a little
earlier and then now there's a third
time scale
with the birth and death of new cells
and maybe even new layers
and that kind of multi-scale
temporal
structuring
is not intrinsic to
the base graph
to represent multiple nested time scales
in a base graph
in the active inference literature it's
more common to make a hierarchically
nested model right and just say that the
time
handling on one level is happening more
rapidly with respect to
clock time than deeper nested slower
models whereas the neural
formulation
allows us to deal with multiple
ongoing time scales
without appealing to hierarchical
nesting
which is very important feature
[Music]
well
yeah both both direction will be
possible so without hierarchical
modeling always
hierarchical modeling so even with
hierarchical modeling the the
optimization of uh dimensionality
should be possible what would be
possible but so in other
Direction so we can consider that a
population of neural models so one has a
single layer another has two layers
three layers host four as and consider
the probability or plausibility or
network architecture
associated with the the
important performance or cost structure
minimization under a particular
environment which is in principle uh
have the same computational architecture
with the the the hierarchical page
[Music]
very interesting yes perhaps I over
generalized or speculated because I
thought about
how one could have a 100 time step
pomdp that also performs multi-scale
Behavior potentially extremely
wastefully but at least it could in
principle and similarly within a neuron
there could be another neural network
[Music]
or some other structure approximated by
that so they almost both enable
hierarchical and non-hierarchical
modeling as you described but in very
different ways
that lead to very different
implementations
yes
I think this brings us to the topic of
forward and reverse engineering
so you talked a lot about
reverse engineering
yeah what is reverse engineering and
what is forward engineering
and what has been done in these areas of
engineering
okay uh I'm I'm not that expert though
but yeah I believe that Lee was here
means uh uh your characterization of the
blueprint of the some you know device or
machine from data observable information
like activity
or action behavior of some agent right
so goal is the identification of the
blueprint
and the cruciary here blueprint
correspond to generality model because
once we Define generative model we can
derive version every energy
algorithm running algorithm interest
algorithm under any behavior of agent so
here because
means that we first observe some
activity of agent and its mechanism is
still unknown for us but we can we can
estimate its mechanisms using uh
in terms of activity by identifying the
most plausible
Journey model which it can minimize some
post function
or or risk function
when we fit the data to
the the model the model so on the other
hand forward to engineering would be a
more mainstream way first Divine model
or blueprint gently model then derive
everything including operation and
parametric functional running in
parasite algorithms and behavior action
uh
section algorithm
so by reverse engineering
neural networks
we're observing some already
parameterized neural network
and then fitting
pom DP to it
to what extent is it possible to take a
given pomdp
and create a neural network
that performs that inference
uh
uh okay in this paper uh or in the
following paper what we consider is the
strategy that we should we first fit uh
empirical data whether for neural
response data to a bus guy produce
canonical neural network model which is
a which is similar to a conventional
model fitting approach where we have a
differential equation and data and fit
data to the differential equation to
explain the the Behavior Uh in the with
the minimal prediction right so now
a virtue of this uh framework we
established is that we can transform we
can actually transform such a neural
network architecture with the
Vernon partially observable Market
division process architecture because
for any a kind of canonical neural
network there is a post-function
so we we derive cross-function from your
activity digestion which is opposite
with the conventional way we first
Define cross-function the right
algorithm and then we use the form of
the Homer
equivalence between neural network cost
function and variational free energy and
so now transform the neural network
architecture to uh Bayesian model
architecture and once we characterize
variational free energy there should be
um some some Journey models that that
Define the the that variationary energy
functional so uh
well in particular this this in this
example uh canonical neural network
nicely correspond to well-known across
of where non-castell
process so by using this this the
procedure we
identify uh approachable home DP
architecture which is a
corresp which correspond to observed
neuropathy data
well
let's
stay on this last
point
so after all those Transformations first
the measurements of neurons
using that data to fit the neural
network and then
by virtue of the relationships unpacked
in the paper
transforming the neural network
in the left side of figure one into
a particular form of the PO mdp so first
what are the constraints on that form of
the pomdp is this little corner of model
space or what are the space of
acceptable pomdps
uh that totally depends on what kind of
neural network model you are considering
so for example
in this paper we discussed about a
particular cluster from DB that in which
each state takes either 0 or 1. so it's
a very restricted compared to the
general form of uh from DB but we have a
we consider a factorization so in the
sense that although each as a
of hidden state where each element
correspond to
one one you know single one hot Vector
but as an entire state it connects the
represent a high dimensional uh discrete
State space
and this architecture nicely correspond
to neural network
architecture because usually each neuron
takes
either 011 or some value continuous
variable between 0 and 1. so uh we use
this Association to characterize a
particular omdp which corresponds to
neural networks and this
allows uh
a particular mean field approximation
approximation or approximation in
genetic model because
we associate a post posterior belief
in this particular form of DB with the
the neural activity
which means that uh posterior of action
also have a factorization architecture
in the sense that we don't uh
we don't fully consider about the the
second order statistics between neural
ones activity and neural activity which
is outside of this homorism
so each
each neuron
near each neurons activity correspond to
uh
posterior expectation about the
particular uh
elements
of the state and we don't consider the
the
[Music]
joint probability joint posterior
probability of all states
so although this is a limit limitation
of uh as we see this as a cluster see as
a Bayesian impressed but
otherwise whatever we can consider any
recurrent Network architecture which
correspond to a state to transition
Matrix
and
it will be possible to extend this
architecture to higher account structure
in the sense that it is
straightforward considered a tree
structure or any kind of a higher card
structure by assuming that some neurons
connect to other neurons but not connect
to
the other neuron so this is same as
considering the hierarchical structure
in general
things that's very
interesting
it's commonly remarked in
the base graphs
that they represent the connections
amongst random variables and there's a
relationship between their computability
and their sparsity
the sparsity structure as in which
variables do or do not influence each
other
makes the problem tractable through
factorization and just kind of
conceptually like if every one of a
thousand variables or an unknown number
of large variables if it was all by all
the number of parameters to fit on that
connectivity Matrix would be very high
so statistical power would be very low
for any given Edge whereas the more and
more constrained you make the
connectivity of the variables the more
statistical power you have to resolve or
kind of spend on fitting those edges
like in a structural equation but you
might be
losing sight of the unknown unknowns by
constraining yourself to a very
limited or fallacious topology of the
variables so there's this kind of
structure learning
statistical inference question in the
base graphs
then
on the neural side from the biological
much of Neuroscience is about
understanding how the firing rate
connectivity patterns and other factors
how the structure of those neural
systems
and their function like Form and
Function
enable
adequate inference and
inference on action
so it's like in both of those areas or
really like in neural network artificial
and neural networks
and in variational Bays
the discussion is about how the
structure and the fine-tuning
work together
to generate function
and about some of the statistical or um
biological challenges of balancing
different needs
while also constraining the cost
in terms of materials and biometabolism
so it's a very rich
intersection
that is being explored here
if these models can really be moving
back and forth
oh
he India says that
popcorn Force
moving back and forth like
there's some imprints of the model that
is implementation independent or like
some interlingua or some semantics
or compatibility I don't really know I
mean that's something we can explore is
like what is it that
is such that one could forward engineer
and then reverse engineer
and have like kind of an expectation
maximization
between these two areas so what is it
that's being
saw
uh yes
to
important point so
yeah for example
about you
of this relationship is that we can use
the knowledge of region inference to
explain your activity neurodynamics
which is crucial because uh people often
say that
characterization character
characterizing neurodynamics is not
straightforward
we we may we may obtain some solution of
neural Dynamics but the meaning of that
Dynamics in terms of functional aspect
is very unclear we don't know the
meaning of connectivity
strength is matrices and what is the
meaning of the threshold factor and so
on so on those are drugs at the derived
from the you know the modeling
physiological phenomena but it is not
necessary to have a clear linkage to a
functional explanation so explanation of
function of the brain but once we
transform cross rate this Dynamics into
a Bayesian influence then we can explain
every functional aspect of the the
neural network Dynamics architecture in
terms of very established Bayesian
difference under a particular class of
Bayesian model in this case pong DB
model
so now uh we talked about that synaptic
strengths correspond to any Matrix B
Matrix which are very established
the Korea meaning
so yeah this is useful to explain the
neural neural synaptic
property
in terms of where established statistics
also for the people in the active
infrared side it would be it would be
helpful to understand the neural nouns
substrate about a particular
active inference modeling model
so so I think it should related to
forward modeling but uh finally to
discuss with the discuss about the
borrowed car substrate of that forward
model we need to address the neural
network
architecture uh
the substrate property so in that
case we can transform a particular form
DP Basia modeling to a neural network
architecture using this relationship and
then get a prediction about the
substrate so if we have this Basia model
this this this particular quantity in
this model should be
foreign
[Music]
oh it's all good can you just repeat the
last like 20 seconds
uh yes so uh in the last part I
mentioned about uh so
first we Define the major model and then
can uh
predict what is a neuronal substrate
that correspond to
ask that the particular evasion model
so this will be useful to so identify
the biological
you know quantities that that correspond
to accounting in Beijing class because
yeah
wow
well
there's a lot
there
it makes me think about the differences
of implementation and heuristics in the
computational setting
which is often in the extreme
disembodied
and the biological setting which is in
the extreme entirely embodied
and
for a given generative model
the kinds of computational heuristics
that can be applied
include a whole host of different
strategies ranging from sampling to tree
exploration and branching
to parallel paralyzing the data
architecture and all these other kinds
of disparate strategies
um and software packages and
implementations
but on the biological side
what is needed
is something that's very simple
but also very
inscrutable
which is a given
pattern of interactions
must embody that calculation
[Music]
um
so that might mean that it can add three
digit numbers but it can't add two digit
numbers
under some constraints
but what isn't accessible to that kind
of morphological biological or like form
and functional Computing was not
accessible are the tree branching
the database decentralization
[Music]
like they're a different set of
heuristics
right but they're both very useful
when we're thinking about making
sentient artifacts
or benefiting simply from the
explainability
across both sides of this figure
yeah so you now others is important
point so holistry it is very non-trivial
whether there is a
corresponding biological architecture or
any given a vision architecture I I
believe it is impossible to design basic
or architecture to respond to arbitrary
region architecture so only a limited
aspect of Asia mother can be implemented
in a vertical portable Manner and that
that point is crucial as a
characterization of biological Network
biological
brain
right
yeah wow well just to kind of
touch again on this forward and reverse
engineering
for a given pomdp
if we're willing to compose it
within a certain class which might be
quite General still
but some class of pmdp
as written on the paper
we may be able to have a neural network
architecture
that would be very amenable to
deep learning low energy computing
pre-training
various features and then on the other
side
for a given
artificial neural network that we come
across
in the wild
or a model
of neurodynamics that we fit using a
neural network model
so something in a neuroscience
Laboratory
that model
can have interpretability
corresponding to the variables of a
given pomdp
and just to kind of give one more point
on how that's going deeper than for
example statistical parametric mapping
SPM
so let's just assume that the neural
network we're dealing with is fit from
brain data from some lucky ant
right now what would be possible
or prior to this line of work or without
this line of work one could
fit a neural Dynamics model
and then do all kinds of analyzes like
power analyzes on the different
frequency Spectra
and say look at the average firing rate
or the correlation core coefficients of
firing rate so fit the firing rates and
the synaptic plasticities and and store
all that data and then we could just
pick a pomdp that we've seen in the
literature
without any reference to the neural
network and optimize the pomdp and then
we could say well it turns out that when
the pomdp
um o is high there's increased Theta
power in this firing pattern
so it's like comparing the descriptive
statistics from the neural model to the
descriptive summary statistics of the
pomdp decision making model
however with this Formal Connection
there is actually an interpretability
to the unobserved neural states which
are what are being inferred from the
fmri measurement from the EEG
measurements and so on
those underlying variables
have a specific interpretability
in relationship to the structure of the
pomdp
right so yeah
that's also a very interesting important
uh aspect
so as you said
what you said is uh I think conventional
more conventional uh strategy and it is
also formally related to model
comparison aspect so we usually think
various major modeling and identify our
select what is the you know best model
to train the given data and this reverse
engineering idea involves such a model
comparison aspect in the sense that we
we try to find the model with the best
best experi ability which should be have
the identical functional right so so we
if directory addresses the the exact
same
uh cost function architecture using the
transformation natural transformation
so uh it should be up to
explain the neural data in the Bayesian
sense
yeah
one can imagine
how that would transform the way that
current neural Imaging studies and
Technologies describe
what it is about the measurement that
provides information
about the cognitive model so to give
another related example let's just say a
person was wearing a EEG headset
and a previous study had shown that
increased
Alpha band activity was associated with
this Behavior
that's comparing a descriptive statistic
of the observations of the sensor
and correlating the summarized
observable to
some other
variable like anxiety or performance on
a behavior
um
in contrast
an unobserved variable
in this setting
the actual underlying
neural state is being correlated
to some
semantic
generative model component
so it's no longer necessarily that any
single frequency band would be
associated
more or less with a given outcome
but it's actually some
hidden state
variability
which gains the interpretability across
this transformation
which is a subtle
point but it speaks to how broadly
the equivalence
would reinterpret
empirical
neuroimaging results
as well as a variety of artificial
neural network
experiments and Diagnostics
where people do lesion studies and
double knockouts on artificial neural
networks
so anywhere
where somebody with awareness sees that
a neural network artificial or
biological
is having summary features described and
correlated to something that's more
semantic
in a quest for meaning
may now have a different approach
that involves
formalizing the model explicitly
in terms of unobserved hidden stage
states with a cost function
akin to a variational free energy
minimizing risk bounding surprise on the
unobservables
so even though the unobservables were
modeled
in a sense
in the other conventional strategy
like neural activity is a variable in
[Music]
fmri experiments it's underlying the
Bold signal
yet this formalism Concordance
is a more
coherent and Powerful connection
he he uh I I I believe so
so uh you now address is very
important point so
it's fast to to to address that so we
need to
clarify about the what is the program uh
considered here so this is a a problem
so-called metavision uh problem in the
sense that researchers try to infer or
estimate uh neural activity or brain
activity which
in for the external World Dynamics right
so neuron or brain info environment and
we researcher in our brain activity so
there is a two-step evasion influence
processes so this sort of metavision
problem is quite uh tricky intractable
uh because sometimes
so probability uh sometimes random
variable becomes uh posterior Greek
about other aspects
so uh I I think there is some
established approach about metavision
but
this is this paper provides some
alternative in the sense that we
separate two problem uh by by saying
that
here uh what we infer is a simply neural
network model or neural network Dynamics
which is shown in the right left hand
side of this this figure so we we feed
the data to Conventional neural network
model which is a simple differential
equation but thanks to this formal
equivalence between neural network
Dynamics and the home DB
Behavior then we can transform the the
resulting neural network architecture
over Dynamics into the
page and influencing in some sense
postcode manner
so we we nicely avoid the
directory addressing the the metabagent
program but obtain the same kind of
solution
I mean that says yes with combining with
brain activity like coding like ieg or
Imaging uh yeah we can we can design we
can we can estimate a plausible neural
network model uh in the left hand side
and we can transform that to pop DB in
the right hand side
right awesome I'm going to show an image
and ask a question from Dave in the chat
so Dave made this image
it's the right side of figure one that
we've just been looking at with the
variational Bayesian formation
and he wrote The Arc shown as impinging
on the S self Arc
is this intentional if so it could
represent tuning or modulation of the
feedback of s into itself
so
do you have a thought on this
uh it's intentional yes uh I think it's
uh related to the usual uh formulation
or or on DB architecture and adaptive
way foreign
[Music]
Matrix B Matrix right so uh here there
the is the alternative or policy and
of Agents so basically the director
indicates a data transition Matrix under
a particular decision
which agent made
in that sense what the agent changes is
a state transition Matrix not the state
itself directory that's why we use this
illustration
awesome
very subtle but important point which is
when we look at the classical
pomdp formulation
so here we'll look at a version shown in
figure two I'll just bring just figure
two in
um
could you describe what you just did
about the role of the B Matrix
in
influencing how hidden States change and
how that is where our policies have
impact
and also please how do the top and the
bottom of figure two
differ
okay so in the in the usual formation uh
under uh
active reference with the Palm DB
structure so we first consider uh
uh the the the pre
prior preference and
depending on the prior prequel as we
compute the expect for energy and its
minimization provide the policy and the
the policy moderate uh there's a state
transition
so now in the upper layer
we instead use the
parital which is the action of the agent
so here caption or decision
was made
for each time step
so that unlike the conventional
formulation so we we have a sequence of
a builder and for each time step there
is a moderate the state transform Matrix
B so B is a matrix that transform
uh as a hidden state in the previous
step to the s in the current time step
and its modulation indicate that under a
specific decision rule uh for example if
this s indicates my our position in the
the battery environment with the gold
decision position moved forward
or if we choose the no-go decision then
it aren't changed so did such a
modulation or or the state transition
was made by choosing Delta and the lower
part uh correspond to uh Bayesian
influence made by
um Beijing agent
so
basically there is a symmetry between
upper part and the lower part because we
assume that this page agent has a
plausible guarantee model which is a
nicely corresponding given environment
defined in the above
a part upper part in this figure
but one
interesting
uh
things so asymmetry is that uh to model
this particular canonical neural network
we don't
consider
an arrow or a link from Delta posterior
to as the posterior which is in the
environment
Delta moderate
uh s in the next step
through b Matrix modulation uh in this
particular
major engine which formally corresponds
to canonical neural network uh we we
don't consider that uh it is correspond
to uh
absence of the
uh projection from output layer to the
the middle the middle layer
just
okay
let's
this is from the uh
2020 paper
but it shows the neural network
architecture the two-layer architecture
so
could you
um
restate
the top and the bottom of figure two
in the 22 paper and connect it to why
it's important that you're studying
two-layer neural network models
I miss your oh yeah can you just connect
um
the asymmetry
between the top and the bottom
on figure two
with the two layer neural network
architecture
you said that the asymmetry there's no
direct link
between
yeah yeah so this this is another story
so in the the previous paper
in the previous paper so there is only a
output rate or or
perceptual because uh we basically
consider a single layer three to four
Network so
my apologize for for some confusion
about the the
Network architecture in the 2020 paper
so now uh upper part of this network
architecture correspond to environmental
genitive process and only a lower part
correspond to a singular single feed for
the neural network architecture
so now
uh this part
is identical to a map from O2 is of
Syria in the
2022 papers
ah
Okay so
on the top of figure two
is the actual generative process
it's the true structure of causation in
the environment which is to say that
actions
Delta
actually influence how States change
Through Time
via B Delta
right
the generative process through the a
matrix emits observations sequences of
observations
and here on the bottom
with a mirrored
structure
is the generative model of the entity
so what's the relevance of the arrows
and the more Forney Factor graph
structure on the bottom
the arrow
indicates the the
influence
or or so it's a it's a crow over the the
information in the sense that to
calculate uh s in the step two we use
the information of step two operation
and step one uh posterior expectation
about hideous State and so do the two
determine the s2's expectation
a usury in the phonograph we consider a
retrospective
Arrow so in the sense that uh S3 also
uh affect the S2 in for us but uh this
this corresponds to a Bayesian smoother
in the sense that we we update every
time step
simultaneously to better
inference however but we consider here
is a more
uh filtering approach in the sense that
for each step we compute the latest
hidden State and then we don't change
any other
states in the past so that's why we
don't consider the r from future to
the past
awesome yeah just to highlight that
in the Bayesian smoothing approach it's
kind of like fitting a spline because it
takes the whole time series and it fits
the smoothest possible line
or the line whose smoothness is on the
AIC Bic Frontier
but here on the bottom
with the
almost pseudocode implementation
provided by the 40-factor graph
which was demonstrated to be equivalent
with the Bayesian graph in the 2017 work
with fristin par and DeVries
this architecture is reflecting a
filtering scheme like a calm and filter
or just generalized Bayesian filtering
Through Time
where
estimates are being carried forward
and changed time point to time point
such that the decision rules or the
updates perhaps more accurately are
defined between time points
and the total time series does not have
to be loaded into memory or Remembered
at once
and then the Bayesian filtering approach
has the asymmetry with a different
consideration of action
so why again is it that action is
considered differently
in the Bayesian filtering approach on
the bottom of the generative model
then the consideration of action in the
generative process
uh these that correspond to uh
connection from y to X in the figure one
or probably
the figure
four is helpful to
the that relationship you also uh
port
oh yeah this is a an example Network
architecture comprising uh input tree
Midori output rail what we consider is a
information flow from sensory to middle
layer and middle area have a self
connections recurrent connection and the
middle area project to Output right here
so there is no connection from all
output area to middle layer
right uh so that's that's why we don't
consider the link from their in the
bottom layer of the figure to to uh s uh
posterior
so this is different from true
generative process in the environment
this is a kind of simplification so
because our purpose is identifying the
the closable bayesia model which
correspond to this this type of three uh
neural network canonical Network
so in other words this canonical neural
network use the approximation about that
point or
uh yeah use limited limited form or
uh pump DP
scheme
thanks so could you describe
w v k and Gamma just what is the
biological
or functional interpretation of those
variables
uh what what brain regions or what
processes or pathologies do they map to
okay so uh basically w v k uh synaptic
strings is uh in the form of matrices
and uh there are different
uh
so they they represent uh Dynamic
Connection in the different layer or
different architecture in the sense that
uh w
means a forward connectivity from
sensory layer to middle layer K
correspond to recurrent Network
recurrent connectivity and V correspond
to uh projection from middle area to
Output clear
so in this paper we don't discuss the
relation to brain anatomy in detail but
one may
be well one can consider an analogy for
example
say
X correspond to uh
several cortex
activity and why why for example
correspond to Sarah Brown in the sense
that it it determined
the
the the action the action
so it is considered that in the serum
there is a signal that represent a
choice this is German for example gold
decision or no gold decision made in and
cerebrum uh it's uh it's a
analogous to this this particular
architecture on the other hand in the
server uh sorry in the several cortex we
compute the the cessary information to
to generate some some inference
prediction and I have planning so on the
way which is computed uh
by this reconnecting Network in this
particular modeling
or do we don't separate realism uh in
detail but this recurrent network is
sufficient to to
network is sufficient to characterize
any type of you know architectures
in the sense that we we can we can yeah
design any uh you know higher car or so
inter so mutually connected uh
architecture using a generic crossover
recurrent Network
by by waitresses
yeah awesome so
the middle layer we can think of as like
the cognitive stuff
it's the internal States when we talk
about perception cognition action
in the active
scheme or even in the sandwich model of
cognition perception cognition action
so
w
is describing how those sensory inputs
either in one step or
composably in multiple steps become
processed
to these X
representations of hidden external
causes inferred external States and so
these are the states that have that
Sigma relationship
and to generalized synchrony with
external States the sigma in the
generalized synchrony are not discussed
in in your paper but it connects to
other work and the recurrent connections
are facilitating
attention or waiting
of the stimuli
this is the recurrent learning Loop and
the relationship of the a between
observations and hidden State estimates
and then a different kind of modulation
comes into play between the hidden State
estimate
of the internal State and the action
selection so what is gamma
corresponding to and why is the gamma
modulation
between layers two and three differing
functionally from the K synoptic
modulation of one and two
yeah so K Matrix uh basically
formally correspond to B Matrix in the
Bayesian home ratio so we propagate the
information about the credit prediction
right our our Nigel our expectation
about the the the next state based on
the previous state
on the other hand uh law of gamma is
quite different from such a computation
gamma basically means a risk factor risk
function which is a
yeah in principle we can we can use
arbitrary risk function so this is the
part of generality model we designed and
the rule of risk function in generative
model formulation is a alternational
form of genetic model depending on the
the value of gamma which enables uh
uh post addictive or
retrospective moderation of the
evaluation and positive decisions
given on outcome uh in the future
uh in terms of neural network uh of
course it corresponds to some
neuromodulation for example dopaminergic
moderation is famous in the literature
which moderate the the activity and
plasticity of various brain region but
we particularly focus on
moderation or any kind of neural
modulation of cyanotic prosthesis in the
output trailer which may correspond to
cerebrum
so you're in the several uh neural
activity or prostitute modulated by
dopaminazi input from uh uh yeah in
uh uh it it is uh used as the
optimization you know uh capturing
decision rule or sometimes attention uh
and bias
uh car pass
awesome very interesting because
in some previous papers and models that
we've looked at
attention
is dealt with as policy selection
on mental States so internal action
selection
is it's an action-like variable
describing attention and awareness and
even metacognition
right and so that connects
the role of dopamine in motor decision
making
seen in many
dyskinesias
but also with the role of dopamine in
seemingly
non-motor based decision-making
like
gambling or investing
where it doesn't seem to immediately
Translate to
a given motor sequence
yeah it has analogous computational
characteristics and the comorbidities
and the side effects of different drugs
that affect the dopamine neurophysiology
are known to have carryover
in terms of like the rigidity or
excessivity of motor and decision-making
aspects so it's like interesting that
dopamine
has long been understood to have that
parallel role
in attention as cognitive action and
motor action
and that was established empirically
through
modifications of dopamine signaling
right and also had been modeled
analogously with computational
neuroscience
and this is providing
again a slightly different
interpretation
[Music]
of that
very well studied dopaminergic
modulation
of attention and policy
yes
and
in addition to that I I believe another
important aspect is a modulation of
scientific processity by dopamine
well
I can
show you um
do you want to show something or
yeah uh can you can you see this
this paper uh I I I sent you you uh a
chat or if you can't uh I'll send you a
PDF
um okay let me see
I'll get it up now
all right the paper is
um
a critical time window
for dopamine actions
on the structural plasticity of
dendritic spines
from 2014.
so what is interesting about this paper
yeah it basically explain uh uh
modulation of plasticity by dopamine
which is hormone uh but crucial point of
this paper is that it shows that it's
proved that dopaminergic input can can
moderate
prosthesis is established so this paper
showed that today add dopamine logic
input for example two seconds after or
several seconds after the the the
heavier
prosthesis is established but such a
post-hoc modulation post-hoc
introduction of
dopaminated sufficient to change the
past plasticity which may be associated
with the the the
post-hoc ba variation of our past
decisions so by decision making we of
course changing the plasticity of
changes with matrix by through
drasticity but to to evaluate
the goodness or Badness of our decision
we need to see observe the future
outcome right which is propagated by for
example dopamine
and this paper nicely show empirically
that
uh dopamine actually uh
it can change the past
decisions evaluation maybe after such a
circuit level very a very local level
microscopic level
hmm
so
there's a short term
window
the critical time window that they're
describing but there's some window
yeah some window yeah
by which
dopamine potentially unrelated to the
initial
heavy and plasticity events
right where secondary dopamine signaling
or
not secondary just after the initial
fact
ually of a different valence or the same
valence can
synergize or cancel
the plasticity formed in the moment
exactly
and this is not limited to dopamine but
other neural modulator can also
do this
well on one hand how does this change
our understanding of animal
neurophysiology
and then I guess on the other hand how
does this influence how we would
design sentient artifacts
one
uh uh the
for both
animals and the same thing
agent artificial agent
on
one one important message I believe is
that so this tells us are
possible simple architecture to make
planning
you this is the association between past
decision and future uh Leeward or any
risk factors which is otherwise computed
by yeah Computing forward prediction by
by iterating some computation right I
believe this is a usual way to to to
predict the future event and then select
the action but uh using this this uh
property physiological property which is
observed in actual experiment uh we can
design we can or imagine other a simpler
architecture to make a planning
so for both animals uh
synthetic Vision agent it provides an
alternative explanation about about the
association between our past decision
and the future please count the
optimization of our decision to maximize
the reward or minimize the risk
well one interesting note is we spoke
earlier about the difference between the
Bayesian smoothing all at once approach
and the Bayesian filtering step-by-step
approach now
if one had infinite knowledge and
computational resources
the Bayesian smoothing approach is the
way to go like you don't want the
decision rule for investment you want to
look at the whole time series past
present and future and know the best
moments to have made the trades I mean
there's no comparison you're going to do
better with the Bayesian smoothing
however it's just impossible
computationally and because it requires
total memory of the past and knowledge
of the future so that's what motivates
the development of Bayesian filtering
approaches
which are tractable and calculable
Through Time
yet
with this time delayed modulation
part of the Bayesian smoothing strength
comes back into play
it doesn't enable true
anticipation of future States
but that's what the expected free energy
does
however the delayed neuromodulation
allows for reconsideration of a window
of past States
and so in that way it corresponds to
um
like a
slightly deeper
filter
not just a filter of a Time step of one
but a filter of like a rolling window of
five or with some decay
and you don't want that window to be too
big because if the window were 10
minutes
then too many
contrasting stimuli would get
um piled together
the dopamine level would just converge
to a mean field average
but there's some time Decay or time
constant
on the post hoc modulation
where that neuromodulatory signal
is actually
a parameter of Interest
and that's not an infinitely long or
infinitely short window but it's some
Niche dependent
amount of time
and that's a very
interpretable and first principles
interpretation
of the computational role of
neuromodulators
in a way that is also consistent with
all these other concordances we've been
exploring so
it's quite an interesting connection
back
I guess in our final minutes of this
discussion
um
what are you
well maybe
go to the beginning at the end
which I meant to ask earlier but it's a
good way that we can sort of close today
and look forward which is how did you
come to this line of research
specifically studying neural networks in
this way
with Carl friston and your colleagues
um
so
yes
well
hmm
so my
my interest was
the the characterization of a basket
biological Network so my my first
motivation is to make a Barclay probable
artificial intelligence but to achieve
that we need to know about biological
brain or biological neural networking
and then
so I in the in these several years uh we
I collaborated with the doctor uh the
professor Cara Christian uh to to study
about his salary create as a principle
of giving for us
and then what my my question
uh going that period was so
is is the free energy principle is
everything about the the you know
biologically possible neurometer or is
there any other another another aspect
uh that can characterize
uh the Barrister neural network so it is
non-trivial uh it wasn't on trivia so
that's why I I try to
so I tried to start from uh
characterizing the neural network first
so our strategy is not
not uh not uh not uh
not considering the way of implementing
any Beijing algorithm as the brain
architecture but our my interest is
rather characterization of a given
vertical Network in terms of
something some other things uh one
possible ways of course based in foreign
Network
and but uh just just defining neural
network architecture is insufficient it
is a two
it is not tractable it is far beyond the
the computational attractability uh as
the mathematical analysis and we need
some
assumption or some some trick to
increase the tractability and one one
day I came up with an idea that uh
so in which we
consider that both new activity across
this the oral the same cost function
gradient this is a very much analogy
with a physical system like lagrangian
formation of hamiltonian Home region so
usually we consider some energy
landscape and
design uh plausible
trajectory as the solution of some
principle of minimum
action or List action so we
imagine that what if we apply such idea
to the neural conventional neuro
canonical neural network of biological
neural network to to characterize their
uh
Dynamics in the the first principle on a
that that's a fast motivation first step
to come up with this this framework
and finally yeah we we noticed that it
is not easy to connect the Newtonian
Dynamics with uh this type of activity
study because uh neural activity
equation not necessary to be a second
order
uh differential equation but
rather it is a first order and
considering many things then we we
yeah finally
use the
cost function uh proposed in the Imports
which is not necessary how a formal uh
identity with the so-called ramadanian
in the Newtonian physics but but it is
rather plausible as the
blue or
underlying mechanism of the such a such
type of network
awesome
well
it has been quite an interesting dot one
I really
appreciate everything you've shared
today
is there anything else you want to add
at this point otherwise we'll talk again
yeah
all right
I already speak girl
thank you all right
talk to you later bye yeah thank you
very much for a nice discussion yeah